Okay everybody,
בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Good to be back. We pick up on
דף daf פ"ו Peh Vav. *Daf Peh Vav* eighty-six at the two
dots, about five lines from the top.
And we are still in the whole issues relating to husband's rights
and their, particularly the husband's rights to the wife's property and so
on, and dealing also most recently with the whole issue about if
a wife takes into the marriage a debt in the name of
other people, I mean other people owe her money, can she waive
the debt, can she be מוחל mochel, *Mochel* the debt? And then
a whole interesting case that we've then transitioned into, which was the
case about a woman who sold her כתובה kesubah *Ketubah* to somebody
else, right? And then the question is,
and then she died, and then her daughter, and then her daughter,
is her daughter in a position to also to waive that debt?
The idea that if somebody is, so the basic principle here being
that you cannot, I don't know how it works in secular court,
but I imagine that it does not work as in הלכה *Halacha*,
because there's an obvious
gaping problem here, which is that in הלכה *Halacha*, what if I
sell you a debt that Michael owes me, say for a hundred
dollars, and I sell
that debt over there to Charlie? It's not like Michael directly owes
Charlie a hundred dollars, because what did I transfer? A debt is
an abstract thing. How do you exactly transfer the ownership of that
debt? And that's a question that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks. And תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says well, maybe if there are liens, then you see
liens as like a type of a partial
ownership or you own the land and you'll be able to exercise
those liens of right to the land, so maybe you can transfer
those. But what do you do when there's no liens? What do
you do when there's no land? So in general, actually, it seems
like I don't really directly transfer that debt to Charlie. Michael still
owes me that money, but I somehow transfer the right to collect
it to Charlie. That's somehow conceptually what happens. But since fundamentally Charlie
collects that money through me and the money is still owed to
me, I'm still in a position to be מוחל mochel *Mochel* and
to waive that debt. Okay? And therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that also if the person who's owed the money dies, the money
is owed ironically even to his heir before it's owed to the
person to whom it was sold. The person to whom it was
sold is really the person who then the money is transferred to.
Imagine that you have a linked bank account, it's sort of what
happens. The money goes into my account when I collect it from
Michael and it automatically transfers to Charlie's account. That's what we've arranged,
the automatic transfer, but not that the money is owed to Charlie.
So therefore if the מלווה *Malveh* dies, then even the יורש *Yoresh*
can waive the debt, because in the end Charlie never directly has
that money owed to him, it's just the money transfers. And that's
the issue about המוכר שטר shtar חובו לחבירו וחזר ומחלו, מחול machul,
*HaMocher Shtar Chovo LeChavero VeChazar UMichalo, Machul*, that I can go ahead
and waive it, ואפילו יורש *VeAfiliu Yoresh*, even the heir can waive
it before the person who bought it is in a position to
collect, to Charlie.
Yeah, I actually mentioned this, in secular law, I can sell a
debt and then I'm completely out.
I understand, that's what I said. This is a very, this is,
this exposes itself to enormous abuse and nobody would buy debts with
this type of a huge loophole.
So therefore obviously, yeah, this, I was going to ask, could we
get some שיעורים *Shiurim* on how you can have capitalism within a
halachic manner? This is, I think there needs to be some big
work on.
Right, so there are some workarounds and we're actually going to get
to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* I'm about to read is going to
be a partial closing of that whole, yes.
Two questions on that. Second, secular law clearly doesn't work that way,
like we just said, so what is the conceptual difference?
Conceptually, well, secular law works a lot better with non-physical objects. So
like the whole idea for example, I don't know, about property rights
and intellectual property, corporations, these are all ideas that
you conceptualize as if it's an item.
Exactly. And הלכה *Halacha* really needs things to be much more concrete.
So that's why it has a much harder problem with this idea
of transferring debts.
And so then my second question then, but essentially if a יורש
*Yoresh* who doesn't have, did not have the debt, right? So it's
abstract vis-a-vis the יורש *Yoresh*, but he can be מוחל mochel, *Mochel*
that. Right. So it does work in a way.
Yeah, but the יורש *Yoresh* is considered to be a continuation of
the person. So it's like the money is owed to the person
itself.
So there is a vehicle for the הלכה *Halacha* to actually, right?
But not by a transfer of the object. No, because it's not
a transfer of the object, it's an identity of the person. The
money is still owed to that person and his heirs and his
estate. It's not like there's an object that's being transferred, right?
To the person who bought it. No, I understand, but that's an
abstract idea.
That is an abstract idea. Yeah.
One that they don't have a vehicle for framing. That is true.
That is true. Yeah.
So this, I mean, is there some principle behind this that would
make more sense to us? Or is the הלכה *Halacha* trying to
discourage the sale of debt or is it just it hasn't considered
the progression?
Yeah, it doesn't seem like it, meaning there's so much about selling
debt and it seems like such a taken-for-granted issue and in כתובות
about a woman selling her כתובה kesubah rights, which has other dangers,
which has dangers because the whole point of the כתובה kesuva is
לא יהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה lo yehe kala be'einav lehotzi'a and all
these types of things. You never get a sense in any of
these גמרות Gemaras that it has any reservations about the institution. You
have a sense that it lacks these sort of legal vehicles, instruments
to make it happen. So, and that's where so that's actually so
let's now take a look as we begin today's דף where it
tries to actually close one of those holes. גופא, Gufa, so let's
take a look. So now we are six lines down on פו.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, המוכר שטר חוב לחברו וחזר ומחלו מחול. hamocher
shtar chov lachaveiro vechazar umechalo, machul. If somebody goes ahead, the guy
who sold it then goes ahead and annuls it, waives it, it's
waived. ואפילו יורש מוחל, ve'afilu yoresh mochal, even the heir can waive
it. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna breih deRav
Yehoshua, ופייסיה. ufeitzachah.
So now here you go, here's already one workaround.
If Charlie went ahead and bought this debt off of me, and
he doesn't want me to waive to waive it to Michael because
Michael still owes me money, מקרקש ליה זוזי, mekarkesh lei zuzei, he
will sort of jingle money in front of
Michael, וכתב ליה שטר בשמיה, vechasav lei shtar bishmei, and have the
debt directly written over to him. So basically, Michael owes me $1,000
and I've now transferred it to Charlie. So Charlie will go to
Michael and say, Michael, I'll give you I'll give you $100 if
you basically directly indebt yourself to me. Now again, it's a little
bit of a question about maybe I'll tear up here's this debt
document I just bought from Dove that says that I can collect
the debt he owes you. I will give it to you, or
I will tear it up and free you from that $1,000 debt
to Dove, if you in
exchange write a $900 debt to me. So you get $100 out
of it. Okay, so Charlie, that's his cost of doing business, because
he bought it off me for less than $1,000, right? He bought
it off me for say $700 or something. Okay, and now Michael
owes him the money directly. So that's what if Charlie's smart, what
he'll do is he'll tempt Michael with some money to get Michael
to directly create a debt between Michael and him, get me out
of the picture, and give him some money for that and tear
up the old debt. Okay, so that's one way around it. Of
course, what you wind up losing is all of those old liens,
besides the difference in money, you lose all those old liens.
In other words, the debtor will say to the new creditor, if
you want to get paid the money, pay a certain service fee
for writing up a new a new bond.
No, the creditor is saying to the debtor, the new creditor, because
if the debtor is smart, he'll go back to he'll go to
me and say, Dove, Charlie just offered me $100, right? I'll give
you so but I still owe 900. I'll give you 500 if
you waive the debt, right? He's in a much better position to
get the whole debt waived coming to me and cutting Charlie out.
So Charlie's got to preempt that before sort of Michael realizes what's
up and get Michael to write a new debt to him, pay
the debtor some money and get a new debt written in his
place. Yeah.
So I technically still owe you the money, not Charlie, right? Right.
So if Charlie comes and is demanding collection, I can say, well,
לאו בעל דברים דידי את? lav ba'al devarimi at?
No, somehow no, somehow, thank you, somehow the writing of the debt
of the transfer of the debt allows him to collect it for
me and allows him to pocket it, but ultimately it's owed to
me.
But so either of you can come, right?
Can you still? No, that's a good point, but no. Some you're
right, it's a funny mechanism. Somehow I've given over those rights to
Charlie. To collect. Right, I can't come, but somehow I can still
waive it.
But let's say I actually paid you, I'm like you know what,
since I technically owe you, then let's say whatever it is, I
paid you. That's strong. Do I say to Charlie well I already
paid you? No. No I can't.
No you can't.
So then there's no I should never pay you.
If I pay
you then I'm still at the money to whoever he sold it
to.
Right, exactly, exactly. It's a funny mechanism.
When the גמרא Gemara here says מחול, machul in other words they
try to prevent him from doing this from being מוחל, mochel like
מיחו ביה? machu beih?
What? מחול means it works. If
I were to be מוחל mochel Michael's debt, it would be the
מחילה mechilah would be effective.
Nevertheless if I pay you it wouldn't be effective? No. Usually when
the גמרא Gemara says לא מיחו ביה, lo machu beih, לא מיחו
ביה חכמים lo machu beih chachamim means they didn't protest. No
no,
that's מוחה.
mocheh. This is מוחל, mochel, מחילה. mechilah. Wait, there's a למד lamed
there?
I have מ-ח-ו. mem-chet-vav. There's a למד? lamed?
Yeah, there's a למד. lamed.
Oh, it's not printed in mine.
Okay. All right, moving on.
So if A sells
a loan, if A sells a loan to B, and then B's
going to deal with and then A forgives it, even though he
sold the same loan to C?
Yeah, so that's the funny thing because it's not fully transferred to
C. C has a right to collect and pocket it, but it's
still owed to B. So that's what's bizarre about it.
But since he
sold it how can he? So isn't he now so that's the
next thing the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to. Doesn't he
owe any money to C if he now went ahead and destroyed
this thing that he just sold, right? Is the
question how can he or why are there no consequences?
It would, it would seem it's no longer his to destroy.
So that's what I, that's why I was saying that conceptually you
do not really fully transfer the debt. What you do is Michael
still owes me the money, Charlie just now has the right, the
sole right, to collect and pocket the money that's owed to me,
but it's still owed to me.
Okay, but you can now forgive it.
Yeah, well, that's Shmuel's חידוש *chiddush* that you can. If it's still
owed for me, I'm still part, I know, it's bizarre. So the
point now is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* exactly tries to figure out
how do we do something to rein this in. Okay, so the
first thing is we give some Charlie advice to cut me out
of the picture. But Michael has to be a little unaware... A,
Charlie has to spend money on it, right, to get Michael to
write a new debt and he has to lose the liens, and
Michael has to be a little bit and Michael has to be
willing, Michael has to be a little unaware that he could get
a better deal by going back to me and seeing what he
could do. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
now says closing the, closing this hole in another direction. אמר מימר
*Amar Meimar* says מימר *Meimar*, מאן דדן דיני דגרמי dinei de-garmi *man
d'dan dinei d'garmi*... distracting me, sit down. אמר מימר מאן דדן דיני
דגרמי מגבי ביה דמי שטרא מעליא *Amar Meimar, man d'dan dinei d'garmi
magbi bei d'mei shetar mealya*. If according to what, מאן דדן דיני
דגרמי *man d'dan dinei d'garmi*, excuse me, מאן דדן דיני דגרמי מגבי
ביה דמי שטרא מעליא *man d'dan dinei d'garmi magbi bei d'mei shetar
mealya*. If the one who judges the laws of גרמי Garmi *garmi*
can collect from me, so I went and I was מוחל mochel
*mochel* Michael's debt, Charlie comes back to me and he collects from
me the full value of the שטרא *shetar*, because what's גרמי Garmi
*garmi*? גרמי *garmi* is a whole set, it's sort of related to
the word of גרמא grama, *grama*, but somehow the adding of the
יוד *yud* is an intensifier and it means there are two concepts
of why I would not pay if I caused damage to somebody.
One idea is גרמא grama, *grama* is indirect. Okay, let's say I
didn't exactly gash your tires but I put tacks right behind your
car, you know, in your driveway. Okay, well you ran over your
whole tire, I guess we could talk about בור ברשות הרבים *bor
bireshut harabim* or whatever, but you could imagine cases. Okay, I put
poison in your animal's feed, I didn't exactly kill your animal where
the actual end result is something that is really destroyed, but somehow
it was a little indirect, that's גרמא grama *grama*. Okay, and when
it's not so indirect, when the causation is more definite or more,
you know, there's more direct lines of connection, that's one concept of
גרמי *garmi*. That yes, certain גרמאs grama *gramas*, high indirectness is פטור
patter. *patur*, but maybe a much closer to direct will be, obligate
you even though it's not technically מזיק mazik *mazik*, if it's not
really physically direct it's not technically מזיק mazik. *mazik*. So logically all
of גרמא *grama* should be exempt, it's one of those formal definitions,
but stuff that is very close to being direct, we'll call that
גרמי *garmi* and maybe there are those that say we'll make you
pay even though technically it's not real מזיק mazik *mazik* because of
the indirectness. So one aspect is the indirectness. The other aspect is
the lack of something that was really destroyed, but there was still
a loss. So for example, let's say I prevent you from going
to work and closing a deal and you lost a million dollars,
opportunity cost or something like that. Or let's say, you know, there
are other types of ways, let's say I go ahead and,
well here's an example that's ours: I tear up, forget that I
sold my שטרא *shetar*, I go ahead and I tear up, Michael
has an IOU against Charlie and I tear it up. Okay, fine,
I'll pay you for the piece of paper. But well, but now
but now Charlie's going to get out of paying me the debt,
he's going to claim there was no debt. That's not my fault,
I mean I didn't destroy the debt, I only destroyed the piece
of paper. Okay, so that's a case where it's not really an
issue of indirect, but the actual, there isn't a, again this gets
to halakhic need of physical,
the
physical object wasn't what was where there was the value. The value
was something that was not actually a physical object that was destroyed,
but there was a significant loss of money. So that's another version
of גרמי *garmi*. So there's a question in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
whether you're דן דינא דגרמי Dina d'Garmi, *dan dina d'garmi*. Do you
basically make people pay for that? And you know, it seems like
that the Rabbis realized that there was this huge gap of unfairness,
this huge area of basically unfairness or injustice that they had to
close, and they made this rabbinic, I mean there's a question is
it דאורייתא *d'oraissa*, is it דרבנן *derabbanan*, whatever, but let's assume it's
דרבנן *derabbanan* and they went and they closed it and they said
cases that fall into that, like a high degree of causation or
definite loss even though there's no physical object, we're going to make
you pay anyway. That's called דן דינא דגרמי Dina d'Garmi *dan dina
d'garmi* but not everybody agreed to that. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying מאן דדן דיני דגרמי *man d'dan dinei d'garmi*, if you're
in the, of that camp that judges these laws of גרמי *garmi*,
מגבי ביה דמי שטרא מעליא *magbi bei
d'mei shetar mealya*. So I go ahead and I מוחל mochel *mochel*
the debt that Michael owes me and Charlie is out all of
his money, I just caused Charlie a thousand dollar loss, right? So
it might be that that works. Great, it works! And now Charlie
can come and sue me for damages. So that's at least one
way to close that gap. I technically retained that right. But if
I do it, I can be sued for damages, דמי שטר מעליא.
dmei shtar malya, Now תוספות Tosfos has an interesting question: how much
is the שטר worth? Okay, if Charlie bought that off of me
for seven hundred dollars and it was a thousand dollar debt, right,
and I מוחל mochel it, how much do I owe Charlie? What
are the two possibilities? Seven hundred dollars, seven hundred dollars or a
thousand dollars? So תוספות Tosfos. says it sounds like when it says
דמי שטר מעליא, it sounds like a thousand dollars. And if that's
true, then that really protects the system. If it's only seven hundred
dollars, it's not so protective. Wonderful. Charlie's going to go through the
whole trouble to buy the debt off of me and then and
then what he'll have to do is then he'll have to spend
court costs and all the time and effort to get back the
exact money he paid. But if either way he's going to get
his thousand dollars, whether he goes to you or whether I מוחל
it and he comes back to me, then that at least protects
the system.
So if you're דינא דגרמי, Dina d'Garmi it pays, you know, how
your fortunes, you know, go, right? So you lose all your assets.
Yeah, let's say you lose your assets and this is true, yeah,
okay. But it is true, it does give another, there is a
little bit of a hole, a weakness there.
But דינא דגרמי Dina d'Garmi here means if you apply that concept.
Yeah, if you feel that people should, that we don't call everything
גרמא, that there are things that are enough real loss even though
they're technically not מזיק mazik. that we make people pay. Okay, even
though so, right,
so if you extend, if you extend this idea to loss beyond
actual physical damage, but right.
For something to be הלכתית halachically damaged, there has to be an
object that is damaged, okay, and you need to do a מעשה
מזיק. ma'aseh mazik. מעשה מזיק. ma'aseh mazik. If you have only one
of those, if you have only a indirect,
you're a גרמא, right, or you are destroying something or you do
a מעשה מזיק ma'aseh mazik that's not an object, that's an abstract
entity, okay, either of that, you're going to be פטור. patter That's
not מזיק. mazik. Okay, but that's a continuum, right? I mean if
you think about it, here's מעשה מזיק, ma'aseh mazik, right, a pure
thing and then there's a whole continuum, right? And here's some type
of a thing that's highly indirect, right? And the actual loss is
unclear and who exactly lost as a result and all those types
of things. I mean again there are like two separate lines because
there's two different issues that are problem. But it's a continuum. So
גרמי is we're going to say we're going to take this piece
of the continuum, the piece that's most closest to real מזיק and
we're going to make you pay. We're going to let you remain
פטור here, but we're going to make you pay in the area
of the continuum that is most close to real מזיק.
So right, so גרמי extends the possibility of culpability for damage.
Exactly, exactly. Yeah.
You said there were two things you needed for
הלכתי halachic damage, one was the object and what was the other
thing?
A direct act. A direct act.
Didn't we also have damages
for embarrassment and things like that?
Yeah, but that's talking about personal damage which is sort of measured
differently, but you're right, there are like גרמא elements there, but personal
injury is a different category. Okay, we're talking about objects. Alright, so
now right, so now the גמרא says like this: okay, מאן דלא
דינא דגרמי, man de'lo Dina d'Garmi, that if you don't make people
pay for that and then somebody goes ahead and is מוחל, so
מגבי דמי ניירא בעלמא. magbi dmei niyara be'alma. You only have to
pay for the paper. And רש"י Rashi says you don't even really
have to pay for the paper because Michael still has the paper,
I mean who has the paper? Charlie, Charlie still has the paper,
okay, so but רש"י Rashi really means is the only thing you'd
ever have to pay for is if I were to destroy the
piece of paper, but there's no debt. The only real thing here
is the piece of paper. You'll never pay for being מוחל the
debt.
Right, but I'm saying that these opinions are called the traditional ones.
Right, so but we basically are דינא דגרמי Dina d'Garmi and therefore
that's a real way to close this gap.
This is the רמב"ן, Ramban, the רמב"ן Ramban has a monographic long
piece about this.
Right, okay. הוה עובדא וכפייה רפרם לרב אשי. hava uvda ve'khafyei Rafram
le-Rav Ashi. There was a case and רפרם Rafram forced רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, you know sort of
compelled רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ואגביה ככישורי דצלמי. ve-agbi be'khitshurei de-tzalmei. And
he made him pay like planks, like beams of wood that you
would use for carving things. Now basically that's obviously some idiom, but
it means he made him pay, what we must have a good
idiom for that? He made him pay like cash money or something,
like he made him pay full in full for it. Now the
question is what does that mean? רב אשי Rav Ashi went ahead
and was מוחל somebody's חוב? chov? I mean says רפרם Rafram forced
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So there's two רש"יs. Rashi This רש"י Rashi
says that it means that רב אשי Rav Ashi wanted to let
the guy off and רפרם Rafram there was sort of persuaded him
to judge דינא דגרמי and said no, no, no, this guy caused
real damage, you gotta make him pay full, it's not just גרמא
and so on. Okay, the other רש"י Rashi in בבא קמא Bava
Kamma says that רב אשי Rav Ashi actually when he was a
kid, רש"י Rashi just makes this up because he's trying to figure
out why would רב אשי Rav Ashi have to pay, did רב
אשי Rav Ashi really do something like this? So he said that
when רב אשי Rav Ashi was a kid maybe he destroyed somebody's
שטרות. shtaros. So then רפרם Rafram when רב אשי Rav Ashi grew
up made רב אשי Rav Ashi pay for for it because of
דינא דגרמי which leads to a fascinating question which is culpability of
children and even though we say that children are exempt from damages.
is some type of דיני שמים dinei shamayim obligation or whatever. I
don't know it's a whole discussion in בבא קמא.
Bava Kamma. With רש"י? Rashi?
Not here. It's רש"י Rashi in בבא קמא Bava Kamma because this
is parallel in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Okay, so דיני דגרמי is
one way to close the gap. אמר מימר שמיה דרב חמא. Amar
Meimar shmei de-Rav Chama. Now we get back, that was a lot
of fun little בבא קמא-ic, Bava Kamma you know, digression and now
we get back to our issues. So האי מאן דאית ליה כתובת
אשה ובעל חוב, hai man de-ika lei kesuvas isha ve-baal chov, somebody
has on against him a כתובה kesuva,
his wife's כתובה, kesuva he divorced his wife so he now owes
his wife a thousand dollars, ובעל חוב ve-baal chov and he owes
some creditors a few thousand dollars. Okay, ואית ליה ארעא ואית ליה
זוזי. ve-is lei ara ve-is lei zuzei. Now,
he has land and he has cash. Okay,
so they're all coming to be paid up. So how do you
decide who gets what? Who gets the cash? Who gets the land?
לבעל חוב מסלקינן ליה בזוזי, le-baal chov mesalkinan lei be-zuzei, to the
creditor we pay cash, לאשה מסלקינן לה בארעא, le-isha mesalkinan lah be-ara,
and to the woman we pay the land.
So
the creditor and his divorcing wife both knocking on his door. Exactly.
He can't get in and his ears are ringing.
It could be, but it sounds like he's alive. האי כדיניה והאי
כדיניה. hai ke-dinei ve-hai ke-dinei. Each one according to their rule, which
means what? Which means the creditor he borrowed cash. If you borrow
cash then you should get back cash. If you don't have cash
whatever you can pay other types of things, but if you borrowed
cash you get back cash. And כתובה kesuva fundamentally was no money
that was actually taken. רש"י Rashi says even though it is true
that part of the כתובה kesuva debt is the dowry, is the
נדוניא, nedunya, but that sort and that might have been cash or
at least objects, but that sort of gets bundled. And fundamentally the
כתובה ketubah. starts as an abstract obligation with liens on land and
that's how it's fundamentally conceptualized. So her fundamental right is to the
land. Now תוספות Tosfos asks an interesting question about, look at this,
take a look at this little תוספות. Tosefos לבעל חוב מסלקינן ליה
בזוזי. le-baal chov mesalkinan lei be-zuzei. אמר רבינו תם דג' דינים חלוקים
למלוה ולניזק ולשכיר. omar Rabbeinu Tam de-gimmel dinim chalukim le-malve u-le-nizak u-le-sechir.
לבעל חוב אית ליה זוזי לא מצי מסלק ליה בארעא.
le-baal chov is
lei zuzei lo matzi mesaleik lei be-ara. For a creditor, if you
have cash on hand, you can't give him land because you took
money you gotta give him money, כדאמרינן הכא. ke-d'amrinan hacha.
וניזק, ve-nizak, if you damage somebody's property, אפילו אית ליה זוזי מסלק
ליה בארעא, afilu is lei zuzei mesaleik lei be-ara, which is interesting.
I damaged your property even if I have cash I can choose
to give you land, which is funny because it's like you're this
innocent person you were injured or whatever, why all of a sudden
should I have the right to give you something that's less like
easily
transferable? Cash you can go ahead and buy a replacement object. So
that's an interesting idea. ובשכיר, u-ve-sechir, one minute, but by a hired
hand, אפילו לית ליה זוזי אמרינן ליה זיל טרח וזבין ואייתי זוזי.
afilu leis lei zuzei amrinan lei zil terach ve-zavin ve-aiti zuzei.
We say that I have to go ahead and I have to
actually get cash to pay you. So it's quite interesting, right? Three
scenarios. One is that you have to pay cash if you have
it but not if you don't. One is that you don't even
have to pay cash. And the other is that even if you
don't have cash on hand you have to get cash to pay
cash. And it's interesting to figure out like why these are split
up this three ways. This is Rabbeinu Tam's approach. I just wanted
to sort of make you appreciate three different types of scenarios. What
did you want... Okay, so let's take a look as the גמרא
continues and it says,
if you used to break my leg, you pay me back by
buying me
land in Vermont.
That's חובל, chovel, that's not מזיק. So the גמרא says like this.
Okay, now האי כדיניה והאי כדיניה. hai ke-dinei ve-hai ke-dinei. ואי לא
איכא אלא חדא ארעא, ve-i lo ika ella chada ara, now let's
say there's only one plot of land. Okay, basically I got multiple
creditors coming to me and I only have limited funds. So the
normal rule would be if I have multiple creditors and only limited
funds then you go by whoever has the earlier lien. Okay, but
let's see what you do here. Okay, I got my ex-wife coming
to me and I got my creditor and I only have one
piece of land. ולא חזיא
אלא לחד,
ve-lo chazya
ella le-chad, and the land is only enough to pay off one
debt. לבעל
חוב יהבינן ליה לאשה לא יהבינן לה. le-baal chov yahavinan lei, le-isha
lo yahavinan lah. We let the בעל חוב baal chov take the
land and not my ex-wife.
What's the difference who got... if you got married earlier?
Yeah, so that's the funny thing. It does not seem to matter
who had the earlier lien. מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the reason?
יותר ממה שהאיש רוצה לישא אשה רוצה להינשא. yoseir mi-mah she-ish rotzeh
lisa, isha rotzah le-hinasei. Because women are more ready to get married
than men. What does that have to do with anything? So תוספות
Tosefos, basically says this is a policy, this is a policy decision.
The policy decision is you want people to lend money and you
want people to get married, right? So based on, now we could
have a rule that's completely blind to the question of marriage or
lend money and just say whoever had the earlier lien and else
whatever we will, you know, otherwise we'll split it if you have
the same time lien. But the reality is that people hopefully stay
married for a long time. Okay, so you have to think about
the policy consequences of this. And if basically we said that you
give it to the woman either in principle or you give it
to the person with the earlier lien which will most often wind
up being the wife, then the implications will be that people won't
lend so much money, right? Why should I go ahead and lend
you money if you're going to have limited funds 50/50, by the
way you'll die before your wife and people get divorced or whatever,
so you know that would... Actually sort of make creditors make people
significant pause to lend money. And the other possibility is okay, but
if we say we give it to the creditor, maybe it'll make
women pause to get married. So he says, you know what, we're
not so concerned that women won't get married. Okay, women are going
to get married. We're more concerned that people won't lend money. So
it sounds like unfair, okay, but in the end you have to
make a policy decision and this was the policy decision. Somebody is
going to be the disadvantaged class, which one can we more tolerate?
And if we let the woman win then people won't lend so
much money. If we let the creditor win then people, women, will
still get married and נעילת דלת.
Ne'ilat Delet. Right.
Okay, so that's how תוספות Tosefos understands that this is essentially a
policy decision. All right.
For תוספות, Tosefos it's stability.
Right. Okay, so he says like this.
Okay, and then okay, and then תוספות Tosefos tries to work it
out if you remember with the discussion on our משנה Mishna בחינא
Bechina where we seem to say the opposite. Remember the משנה לקשות
שבהן Mishna Lakushot shebahem and some say it means לכתובת אשה משום
חינא Liksuvas Isha Mishum China and there it seems to be that
we favor the woman over the creditor. So תוספות Tosafot works to
explain how those circumstances are different.
Okay, but this was again to protect the woman. Especially this is
her way, a creditor might have another way of getting by, this
woman might not.
I understand, so that's your other point which is right, which is
not that the policy considerations about will it stop people from lending
money or get married but what is going to be the who
is going to be
the impacted by this policy right, who can manage the negative implications
of this better the creditors or the woman? Exactly. Beautiful. So we
will continue with this issue later about multiple people coming with multiple
debt claims etc. Okay, but anyway that's what we're saying now that
we give it to the creditor. אמר ליה רב פפא לרב חמא.
Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Rav Chama. So רב פפא Rav Pappa said
to רב חמא. Rav Chama. וארי דמיתני משמיה דרבא. Va'ari d'misni mishmei
d'Rava. Is it true what I heard you said in your name
and the name of רבא? Rava? האי מאן דמסיק ביה זוזי ואית
ליה ארעא. Hai man d'masik bei zuzei v'is lei ara. If somebody
owes money to somebody and he has land. ואתא בעל חוב וקא
תבע מיניה. V'asa ba'al chov v'ka tva minei. And the creditor comes
and demands the debt. ואמר ליה זיל שקול מארעא. V'amar lei zil
shkol me'ara.
And he says to him sure go ahead take my land. אמרינן
ליה לא זיל זבין את ואייתי הב ליה. Amrinan lei lo zil
zavin at v'aisi hav lei. No we say to him you can't
just give him the land you have to sell it, you have
to sell the land and give him money. Okay so this is
the question תוספות Tosafot raised if you have both cash and land.
I'm sorry excuse me. He only has land. Are you allowed to
give him the land? We said if you have cash you have
to give him cash. But let's say you don't have cash on
hand you only have land. Can you give him the land or
do you have to basically convert it to cash? So he said
I heard in your name that you have to convert it to
cash. אמר ליה לא אימא לי גופא דעובדא היכי הוה. Amar lei
lo eima li gufa d'uvda heichi hava. No I never said that.
Tell me exactly what happened what you heard that this report was
that I made a guy sell the land in order to give
cash. אמר ליה תלא מעותיו בעובד כוכבים הוה. Amar lei tola maosei
b'oved kochavim hava. What he did was he had the cash to
pay. Okay so Michael came to me for the thousand dollars I
had the thousand dollars but I didn't want to give my thousand
dollars I wanted to get rid of my junk land. So what
I did was I found my friend Christopher and always a good
non-Jew Christopher and I gave him I said here Christopher hold on
to this thousand dollars for me or I made some fake type
of a way that I transferred it to his title to him
so that when Michael came to me I didn't have the cash
in hand. I bought his חמץ chametz with it right.
And then I said
oh Michael I don't have any cash here take the land. הוא
עשה שלא כהוגן לפיכך עשו בו שלא כהוגן. Hu asa shelo k'hogan
lifichach asu vo shelo k'hogan. So he acted inappropriately to Michael and
therefore we forced me to sell the land even though yes if
Michael really had come to me and all I had was land
and I really had bought something off of Christopher then I could
have given Michael the land. But since I only bought it off
of Christopher so that I could keep the money away from Michael
then we forced me to go ahead and get the money to
pay off Michael. But this then shows that even though the בעל
חוב ba'al chov is entitled to cash if I have cash. If
I don't have cash and I'm not playing any tricks I can
give him the land that I've got. Okay so now the גמרא
continues. אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב פפא. Amar lei Rav Kahana l'Rav
Pappa. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to רב פפא. Rav Pappa.
לדידך דאמרת פריעת בעל חוב מצוה. L'didach d'amart prias ba'al chov mitzva.
You say that paying off the creditor is a מצוה. mitzvah. So
if a person were to say לא ניחא לי דאעביד מצוה lo
nicha li d'avid mitzva what? I don't want to do the מצוה.
mitzvah. Okay now we say if somebody said paying off a creditor
is a מצוה mitzvah that's an additional obligation. In addition to any
types of monetary rights and דיני ממונות dinei mamonos there's a מצוה
mitzvah to pay off your בעל חוב. ba'al chov. But what actually
emerges from the גמרא this is based on that רב פפא Rav
Pappa holds that... is a מצוה mitzvah and that מצוה mitzvah is
necessary in order to get the guy to pay. So what would
be the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? נפקא מינה nafka mina is that
somebody died, owes money, and he leaves under-age children in charge of
the estate. Can the person collect the debt, right, from the estate
while the kids are under age? No, because here's the problem. If
you say all it is is monetary rights, I have rights in
this guy's land, I have a ליין, lien, I'm going to exercise
it, right? So assuming that like I have a שטר מקויים shtar
mekuyam and there's no issue that I'm owed the money, why can't
I exercise my rights? But if the idea is that what allows
me to collect is not just my monetary rights, but partly is
the idea that this person is doing a מצוה, mitzvah, and that
sort of enables me. Well, you've got a מצוה mitzvah to do
it and I've got these monetary rights, somehow that's part of the
mechanism that allows me to collect. The kids aren't yet obligated in
the מצוה. mitzvah. Right, so therefore even with my ליינס, liens, I
can't collect until they grow up. That's רב פפא Rav Pappa's idea.
That you need, there is a מצוה mitzvah and that you need
the person to be obligated in the מצוה mitzvah in order to
enable you to collect. Partly maybe what this is dealing with is
the implicit idea of, you know, force. That's part of all types
of collections, right? How do I go ahead and force you, compel
you? So if you have the idea, well you're מצווה mitzuveh in
it, so that maybe enables part of that mechanism to work. So
then it can be both. So then, no it is both. It
is both. That's why I said you've got the ליינס liens but
for the ליינס liens to work. תוספות deals with the question of
what if you don't have the ליינס liens at all but let's
just now it's not fully our סוגיא. sugya. You have the ליינס
liens but in order for the ליינס liens to work for רב
פפא Rav Pappa you also need the person to be obligated in
מצוות mitzvot and to have the מצוה. mitzvah. And that's part of
his mechanism. So then comes along רב כהנא Rav Kahana and says
to him, so let's say the guy is not a minor, he's
an adult and he says, 'You know what? I don't want to
do the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay? So the only way you can make
me pay is through my מצוה mitzvah obligation? I'm choosing not to
do the מצוה.' mitzvah. So would you really let the guy go
off scot-free? Or the way תוספות says it is obviously you wouldn't.
How do you justify working if you need the idea of מצוה
mitzvah to be part of your mechanism? So, מאי? mai? אמר ליה,
amar leh, תנינא. tanina. Ah, here's how I'm going to make it
work. We taught, במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is it
that you give lashes? במצוות לא תעשה. be-mitzvot lo ta'aseh. If he
transgresses a negative prohibition. אבל במצוות עשה, aval be-mitzvot aseh, but if
it's a positive מצוה mitzvah where they say to him עשה סוכה
ואיני עושה, aseh sukkah ve-eini oseh, לולב ואיני עושה, lulav ve-eini oseh,
make a סוכה, sukkah, make a לולב lulav and he refuses to
do it. So it's not through lack, it's not through past transgression
of a positive מצוה mitzvah but it's refusal to fulfill a positive
מצוה. mitzvah. מכין אותו עד שתצא נפשו. makin oto ad she-tetze nafsho.
You're not even limited to forty. You can beat him up to
the verge of death or maybe literally means death. Anyway, we can
compel people to do מצוות. mitzvot. Right, the difference between that you
give lashes for a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh is transgression. If you
transgressed a positive מצוה, mitzvah, סוכות Sukkot is over, we're not going
to give you lashes for not taking your לולב. lulav. But if
it's still during סוכות, Sukkot, talk about כפיה דתית, kfiyah datit, right?
Ha ha! We can basically use physical force to get people to
do מצוות. mitzvot. So basically his answer is, yeah, it's true, it's
a מצוה mitzvah but you can force people to do מצוות. mitzvot.
But they have to be obligated, if they're minors they're not. Okay.
Yes. You know what I don't understand about that is like, I
understand if you say it's a מצוה mitzvah as part of the
mechanism. In other words, really it's a divine command, G-d in economy,
it's between G-d and history. Okay so you didn't want to act
on your מצוה, mitzvah, on your ציווי. tzivui. But that doesn't mean
the mechanism is not there. Why do you need to compel? In
other words, you know what I'm saying? No, because I think that
the whole idea of requiring a מצוה mitzvah is, like I said,
is that like, how do we use force to get you to
like, you know, like when you owe me money and you're not
paying, right? The sheriff comes, he brings his, you know, they come
and they seize your property. Right? That's the imposition of force on
you. Against your will. What allows that? Right, so you know, against
your will it's too bad, you're obligated. Right, right. Is it by
a serious principle or is this granting discretion to the court? Yeah,
granting discretion to the court. We don't go ahead and force everybody
we see not doing מצוות. mitzvot. And also it's like so imaginary
because if you read it, like, you know, other stories and what
we know historically, like, you know, so many people were violating in
so many different ways. חז"ל Chazal didn't really have the power to
stop it at all. Like in some theoretical model, you know, we
could force people if we actually had that power and if we
actually chose to do it. Right. But isn't there something missing from
the whole construction of these scenarios is the issue of time? You
know, we all know that you might want to sell your property
today, but last year the prices were depressed and you wouldn't want
to. Right, so that's a סוגיא sugya in ערכין Arachin about מסדרין
לבעל חוב, mesadrin le-ba'al chov, which is creating a payment schedule or
you know giving him time in order that the creditor could be
paid up in a timely fashion but that the debtor could have
the time to dispose of the property in a way that it
doesn't you know that allows him to Oh no, all of this
is that it's due now. I mean, obviously you can't make anybody
pay before it's due. But the question is it doesn't matter how
much overdue it is, like you know, the whole issue about מסדרין
לבעל חוב Mesadrin L'Baal Chov is once you start the process with
the court, then a certain timetable kicks in. But all of this
is a discussion only from the moment it's due. All right, let's
keep on going. בעי מיני רמי בר חמא מרב חסדא. Boei minei
Rami bar Chama meRav Chisda. See, I come back and we fall
behind. Rami bar Chama asked Rav Chisda: הרי זה גיטך. Harei zeh
gittech. Now, this is going to be it's like funny how we
jump between topics. Right, was talked a lot about חובות chovot and
being מוחל and how do you collect חובות, chovot, etc. And now
we're going back to you'll see the comparison that gets to, like,
a first, an earlier case in our Mishna. Okay, somebody says to
a woman: This is your get, ולא תתגרשי בו אלא לאחר שלשים
יום. velo tigarshi bo ela achar sheloshim yom. הלכה והניחתו בצידי רשות
הרבים. Halecha vehinichato betzidei reshut harabbim. מהו? Mahu? So does it work?
So this might, remember, is very similar to a case we had
before about something taking effect after thirty days and to what degree
is some of the remnant of the קנין kinyan still present? אמר
ליה, amar leh, so he said: What's the question? What does צידי
רשות הרבים tzidei reshut harabbim have to do with this? Because if
you need, when something takes effect later, if you still need to
have some degree of that sense of possession at the time when
it takes effect, so if it's in, you know, you'll see, we'll
this will be the case. Is it מפקיר mafkir the get? Not
מפקיר mafkir it, but if it takes effect later, you might still
need some of that original sense of that act of קנין kinyan
to be demonstrated at that time. Is being in the צידי רשות
הרבים tzidei reshut harabbim like
being in her possession because
people have certain rights in the areas in, like, on the sidewalk?
Okay, in the middle of the street, you have no personal space.
On the sidewalk, you have a certain amount of personal space. So
is that still like it's under her control and a remnant of
that original קנין kinyan of being in her hands that it takes
effect after thirty days? This was in context of the סימטא. simta.
Exactly, which is מעכשיו. m'achshav. Well, okay, so we'll talk about that
in a minute. אמר ליה, amar leh, אינה מגורשת, Einah megureshet, she's
not divorced, מרב ושמואל. mi-Rav uShmuel. For based on Rav uShmuel, דרב
ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, deRav uShmuel de'amri tuvaihu, they both say: והוא שצבורין
מונחין ברשות הרבים. ve-hu she-tziburin munachin bi-reshut harabbim. You might remember in
our Mishna, which got onto this discussion by the cow, right, was
the case about a person dies and he has cattle and cattle
is normally not, there are no liens on the cattle. But nevertheless,
if the cattle was, you know, in the, like, in the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, there might be cases where the creditor or the
wife would have would have right, you know, they seized it after
the guy's death, remember the whole discussion, before the guy's death, after
the guy's death, they seized that cattle, that might give them rights
to collect from that cattle. But the Gemara says, but it must
have been that when he died, it wasn't under the control of
the heirs. How was it that it wasn't under the control of
the heirs? Oh, it was in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. So
what do you see? You see that being in a רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim means not under the control of the person. So similarly
by this case of get, assuming that her קנין kinyan will only
work thirty days from now, if it's still under her control, so
being in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is not being in your control.
Okay, so מרב ושמואל mi-Rav uShmuel it doesn't work. What about צידי
רשות? tzidei reshut? Okay, so it's assuming צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshut
harabbim is like רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. דרב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, deRav
uShmuel de'amri tuvaihu, they both say: והוא שצבורין מונחין ברשות הרבים. ve-hu
she-tziburin munachin bi-reshut harabbim. When the heir's property is in the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, it's might be owned by them but not under
their control and it lets the creditor seize it. So you see
רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is not under your control. וצידי רשות הרבים
כרשות הרבים דמי. Ve-tzidei reshut harabbim ke-reshut harabbim dami. Right. And I'm
assuming that the sides of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim are like a
רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and therefore it's not under her control and
therefore it won't be a good get because it needs to be
under your control when the get takes effect. אדרבה, Aderaba, says the
Gemara, say the opposite: מגורשת מרב נחמן. Megureshet mi-Rav Nachman. I should
use Rav Nachman's teaching to tell me she is divorced. דאמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה: De-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha:
האומר לחבירו, Ha-omer le-chavero, and this is ממש mamash clearly the case
it was modeled after: משוך פרה זו ולא תהא קנויה לך עד
לאחר שלשים יום, meshokh parah zu ve-lo tehei kenuyah lekha ad achar
sheloshim yom, draw this cow to you and it should only be
owned by you after thirty days, קנה, kanah, he owns it, ואפילו
עומדת באגם, va-afilu omedet ba-agam, even if after thirty days it's in
a swamp. So a swamp is like a סימטא, simta, it's like
an alleyway. So because it's not private property but it's not like
a public thoroughfare. So you see being in some type of a
semi-private space, non, not the middle of the thoroughfare is enough under
your control for something to work, a קנין kinyan to work at
a later time. מאי לאו היינו אגם והיינו צידי רשות הרבים? Mai
lav haynu agam ve-haynu tzidei reshut harabbim? Isn't a swamp and the
alleyways, isn't that like the sides of the רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim?
That it's enough not in the public thoroughfare that it's enough under
your control. So therefore it should work. לא, lo, no, אגם לחוד
וצידי רשות הרבים לחוד. agam le-chud ve-tzidei reshut harabbim le-chud. No, the
swamp is one thing and the צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshut harabbim
is another. צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshut harabbim is so close to
the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim it's considered to be like רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. So the end of the day is we all agree
to the principle: it's got to be under your control for it
to take effect thirty days later. The question is and certain things,
alleyways and swamps are under your control. איכא דאמרי *Ika de-amrei* some
say אמר ליה מגורשת מדרב נחמן *amar lei megureshet mi-derav Nachman* that
she is divorced based on Rav Nachman, דאמר רב נחמן וצידי רשות
הרבים כאלגם דמי *de-amar Rav Nachman ve-tzidei Reshush Harabbim ke-algam dami* and
the sides are treated like the אגם *Agam* and therefore it is
under her control. אדרבא אינה מגורשת מדרב ושמואל *Adiraba eina megureshet mi-derav
u-Shmuel*. No, she should not be divorced based on Rav and Shmuel
that say being in רשות הרבים *Reshush Harabbim* is not under somebody's
control for the idea of the whole seizing of the property, the
heirs. מאי לאו היינו רשות הרבים והיינו צידי רשות הרבים *Mai lav
hainu Reshush Harabbim ve-hainu Tzidei Reshush Harabbim*? Presumably, the sides of the
רשות הרבים *Reshush Harabbim* are like the רשות הרבים *Reshush Harabbim*? לא
רשות הרבים לחוד וצידי רשות הרבים לחוד *Lo, Reshush Harabbim le-chud ve-Tzidei
Reshush Harabbim le-chud*. No, the public thoroughfare's one thing, the sides' another.
This is a general question that comes up in the גמרא *Gemara*
in many different contexts whether צידי רשות הרבים כרשות הרבים דמי *Tzidei
Reshush Harabbim ke-Reshush Harabbim dami* in many, many areas of הלכה *halacha*
that care about the idea of רשות הרבים *Reshush Harabbim*. So anyway,
this was a nice way of getting back to an earlier point.
Remember the משנה mishna *mishnah*? We really digressed on the משנה mishna
*mishnah* about all this fascinating stuff about owing debts and מוחל *mochel*-ing
debts and גרמי *garmi*. But going back to the משנה mishna. *mishnah*
about who has rights to the chattel, can the woman collect from
the chattel if she seizes it and so on? We revisit this
idea of being in the רשות הרבים *Reshush Harabbim*, being under control,
and this idea of a קניין לאחר זמן *kinyan le-achar zman*. Michael
reminds us, as תוספות *Tosafot* does, that this whole thing only works
if you said מהיום *me-hayom*. Remember that? The גמרא *Gemara* said it's
different if you said מהיום *me-hayom*. So תוספות *Tosafot* says you have
to assume you're saying מהיום *me-hayom* here. Yes. I thought you would
just finish. I asked how decentralized should we understand these practices to
be? In other words, in one city the woman would be divorced
and she goes to the other city she wouldn't be? Well, the
גמרא *Gemara* is making it in the end that there's not a
debate of Rav and Shmuel and Rav Nachman. They both we פוסק
*posken* both of them, and which one do you use as the
model to apply to this case? But, yes, we do find other
cases that different, you know, there was not a unified הלכה *halacha*
that there were different פסקים *pesakim* in different locales. Certainly. I mean,
but emphasizing the case of your marital status is a huge נפקא
מינה *nafka mina*. Clearly. Is there just a fundamental question here whether
the woman has to accept the גט *get*? I mean, here's your
גט *get* to be effective in thirty days. Yes, so that's the
point. You have to put the גט *get* into her control. She
doesn't have to be willing, but it has to be put into
her control, thrown into her hand, thrown into her yard. But if
she doesn't want to be divorced and you say לאחר שלושים יום
*le-achar shloshim yom*, then she's got a way of getting out of
it. Make sure that, yes, so if she goes ahead and she
tears it up or whatever, she's good if she doesn't want to
be divorced. Exactly. That would be a way. The same way if
you don't want to be served, you know, a what do you
call it, a subpoena, and you go ahead and you hide and
whatever. So, yeah, I mean, even though a woman can be divorced
against her will, you have to either find her or her property
in order to put the גט *get* into for to make it
effective. And so this would be a case like it took place
thirty days from now and if it's torn up, she's made it
not take effect. Okay, next משנה mishna. *mishnah*. המושיב את אשתו חנונית
*Ha-moshiv es ishto chenvanis*. Somebody basically is a storekeeper and he got
married and he put his wife to work. And now she's, go
ahead, and she's running the store. או שמינה אפטרופיא she-mina apitropia: *o
she-minah apitropya*, or made her like a what do you call it?
An אפטרופיא *apitropya*. A guardian. Right. It's like a, yeah. אפיטרופיס *Apitropis*,
right? Yeah, it means like basically he gave her power of attorney
over the estate. Okay? He gave her rights to the bank account
and whatever, he put her in charge of the business and about,
and over his property. הרי זה משביע כל זמן שירצה harei ze
mashbi'a kol zman she-yirtze: *harei zeh mashbia kol zman she-yirtzeh*. So, basically,
the way you get your workers to know that they're not skimming
is not that you bring in an accountant and do an audit,
but you actually make them take an oath. And you say, I
want you to take an oath to say that you haven't, you
know, pocketed any money, you haven't skimmed anything, you haven't cheated on
the books. And they have to take an oath. So, he says
that, okay, so the husband can do that to his wife, can
make her take an oath. You can imagine that's going to do
wonders for the marriage. If it's her property and he's working for
her, yeah. Okay, it's not a question about men and women. Right.
Okay, so but we'll see why, how this plays out as the
גמרא *Gemara* continues. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer: *Rabbi Eliezer
omer*. Rebbi Eliezer says, אפילו על פילכה ועל עיסתה *afillu al pilchah
ve-al issasah*. No, you can even make her swear not just in
those special cases where you could normally make your workers take oaths
to you. But look, if she's going ahead and she's knitting in
the house, the פלך *pelech* is the what is this, the spindle
or something? Or if you go ahead and, you know, you buy,
you pay for the food bill, maybe she's skimming from something from
the soup? Not just skimming from... she's maybe, maybe she's keeping or
maybe she's pocketing the dough. But the... sorry, that was bad. Anyway,
so, any kind, any normal case, the woman is in charge, right,
a woman is in charge of the domestic responsibilities. How do you
know she's not pocketing some money there? So, a husband even under
just normal cases, wife isn't doing any work, just in the house,
he can make her take oath that she isn't cheating, skimming anything
from him, that she isn't cheating him. Okay. Yeah, but exactly about
how jealous the husband in is, how much we allow for that.
So let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*. He's making oath
bread. Oh my God. איבעיא להו *Iba'ya lehu*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
על ידי גלגול קאמר *Rabbi Eliezer al yedei gilgul ka-amar*, which one
also wonders if there's a little bit of a pun there. Not
really, but you know, to מגלגל *megalgel* the עיסה *issah*. But גלגול
*gilgul* means that if I already am entitled to make you take
an oath over one thing, I can throw into that oath... to
make you take an oath over many other things. Okay, so is
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying in the case of the storekeeper where
you're already entitled to make her take an oath because she's your
employee and she's working in the store? You can then make her
take an oath over all the domestic stuff as well. So it's
only once you're already entitled to make her take an oath. Or
לכתחילה? le-chatchila? Does he mean even without being a storekeeper? You can
just a husband can סתם stam say to his wife, 'Swear to
me you haven't taken any of the grocery money.' תא שמע: Ta
shema: Come in here. אמרו לו לרבי אליעזר: Amru lo le-Rabbi Eliezer:
They said to Rabbi Eliezer, אין אדם דר עם נחש בכפיפה. Ein
adam dar im nachash bi-kfifa. That's not tolerable. A person cannot live
with a snake in the same, under the same roof. So basically
he's the snake, right? Sometimes that's used to describe him, sometimes it's
used to just describe her. So basically it makes it a completely
intolerable marriage that there should be that lack of trust that he
can't even trust her in terms of the groceries. So and that
he could make her swear at any time. Apparently that's not a
big enough of an issue in terms of the running the store,
but okay. Okay. אי אמרת בשלמא לכתחילה: Ee amart bishlama le-chatchila: If
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying that he can just do it
סתם, stam, so שפיר, shapir, it's okay, you understand the rabbi's response.
That's intolerable. אלא אי אמרת אדי גלגול: Ela ee amart adei gilgul:
So but if you can only make her swear once as packaging
it in with another oath, מאי נפקא לה מינה? mai nafka la
mina? So why does she care? Meaning if it's not like he
can just סתם stam make her swear anytime he wants on this
type of thing. If it's when she's already being forced to take
an oath on something else, so you want to throw other things
in. Why does that matter once she's already taking an oath? So
the גמרא says, you know what? It does matter psychologically. It's not
maybe that he can do it more times, but it's right. It's
psychologically, exactly. It undermines any sense of trust. דאמרה ליה: De-amra leh:
she says to him, כיון דדייקת בתראי כולי האי: keivan de-daikat batrai
kulei hai: You are so exacting. You know, it's one thing I'm
managing your million-dollar business or whatever, you don't trust me. But you
don't trust me on the few dollars for groceries? לא מצינא למידר
בהדך: lo matzina le-meidar bahadach: it's intolerable. I cannot continue to live
with you if you can't even trust me over the few dollars
for groceries. תא שמע: Ta shema: Come in here. A ברייתא: braita:
הרי שלא פטר את אשתו מן הנדר ומן השבועה: Harei she-lo patar
et ishto min ha-neder u-min ha-shvu'a: We're going to see in the
next משנה mishna. that a man can actually exempt his wife from
ever having to take a vow. This משנה mishna. is in a
way a lead-in to the next משנה. mishna In principle he can
make her take a vow, but he can also basically waive her
and say, 'I will never make you take a vow.' That's going
to be the next משנה. mishnah. So if he did not exempt
her from taking vows, והושיבה חנונית: ve-hoshiva chanuvit: or שמינה אפטרופיא: and
he made her a storekeeper or somebody in charge of his property,
of his estate, of his business, הרי זה משביע כל זמן שירצה:
harei ze mashbi'a kol zman she-yirtze: So if he didn't waive his
rights to make her take an oath, he can make her take
an oath any time he wants. לא הושיבה חנונית: Lo hoshiva chanuvit:
Now let's say she's not a storekeeper, ולא מינה אפטרופיא: ve-lo mina
apitropia: and she's not in charge of his business, אינו יכול להשביע:
eino yachol le-hashbi'a: he cannot make her take an oath over domestic
types of things. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר: אף על פי שלא
הושיבה חנונית ולא מינה אפטרופיא, af al pi she-lo hoshiva chanuvit ve-lo
mina apitropia, הרי זה משביע כל זמן שירצה: Even in non-special cases,
a husband can always make his wife take an oath. שאין לך
אשה שלא נעשית אפטרופיא שעה אחת בחיי בעלה: She-ein lecha isha she-lo
na'asit apitropia sha'a achat be-chayei ba'ala: because there will always be one,
at some situation where effectively she is in charge of his money,
על פלכה ועל עיסתה: al pilka ve-al isata: on her spindle or
on the dough that she's making into חלה. challa. So there'll always
be circumstances where she's using his property. Right, so it's explicit that
it's not a case of the storekeeper. It's even לכתחילה. le-chatchila. אמרו
לו: Amru lo: אין אדם דר עם נחש בכפיפה: ein adam dar
im nachash bi-kfifa: You cannot live together with a snake. שמע מינה
לכתחילה: Shma mina le-chatchila: you see that רבי אליעזר says the husband
is entitled to make her take this oath even without any context
of being a storekeeper. שמע מינה: Shma mina: you see that. By
the way, I think it's interesting to string together a number of
positions of רבי אליעזר about women. Seems to have had a very
particular approach. I think he was the one that said that you
can't, you can't be מלמד את בתו תורה כאילו מלמדה תפלות. melamed
et bito Torah ke-ilu melamda tiflut. I think רבי אליעזר has a
lot of things that we would sort of see as less sympathetic.
There you go. Okay, let's just read the next משנה. mishnah And
this is now the second part of the previous משנה. כתב לה
נדר ושבועה אין לי עליך: Katav lah neder u-shvu'a ein li alayich:
The basically man writes to the wife, this is similar to the
beginning of the משנה like he said like, 'I don't have any
rights to your פירות,' peirot, waiving his rights. So he can also
waive his rights in terms of the oath. He says, 'I will
never make you take a נדר neder or שבועה shvu'a to me
over anything.' אינו יכול להשביע: Eino yachol le-hashbi'a: he can no longer
make her take an oath. By the way, the way a נדר
neder would work is she would say, 'If I stole anything from
you, let all the fruit of the world be forbidden to me.'
That's a נדר. neder. A שבועה shvu'a is an oath that I
did not steal anything from you. So if he basically writes and
says, 'You'll never be required to do that,' then he can no
longer make her take an oath. Or right, or separate from the
כתובה. ketubah. אבל משביע הוא את יורשיה ואת הבאים ברשותה: Aval mashbi'a
hu et yoresheha ve-et ha-ba'im bi-rshuta: but he said, 'I exempted you
from an oath.' If she dies, then he can go ahead and
make her heirs take an oath in terms of things that they
might have to take an oath about. Not in terms of running
the store, whatever that was presumably only she was doing, but for
example, when the heirs come to collect the כתובה. ketubah you can
maybe make them take an oath that they haven't already been paid
and other types of things. So the point is that this only
works for her. It does not work for any heirs. נדר ושבועה
אין לי עליך ועל יורשיך ועל הבאים ברשותך. neder ushvu'a ein li
alaich ve'al yorshaich ve'al habaim birshutaich. Now you see how it parallels
the first משנה. The people that she sold her כתובה ketubah to
somebody, okay, and then that person comes to collect, so I've only
exempted you. Nobody else who is coming somehow because they inherited your
כתובה ketubah. or you sold them your כתובה. ketubah Now, let's say
he says I will not make you take an oath or a
vow, אין לי עליך ein li alaich or your heirs take a
vow ועל יורשיך ועל הבאים ברשותך ve'al yorshaich ve'al habaim birshutaich or
anybody that comes through your power, like you sold your כתובה ketubah.
to, I will any I cannot make any of them take a
vow about anything relating to like you and your כתובה. אין יכול
להשביע, ein yachol lehashbi'a, I cannot make her swear, לא היא ולא
יורשה ולא הבאים ברשותן. lo hi ve'lo yorsha ve'lo habaim birshutan. Not
she and not any of these other people that are coming through
her power. אבל, aval, but here's the one case I did not
accept: יורשי משביעין אותה ויורשיה ואת הבאים ברשותן. yorshai mashbi'in otah ve'yorsheha
ve'et habaim birshutan. I said I won't make them swear to me.
But if I die, my heirs can come and make my wife
swear that she didn't cheat off of the business or that her
you got it? So I said she doesn't have to swear to
me, but my heirs can make her swear that she didn't cheat.
Okay, now let's say so how would you close off all the
avenues? נדר ושבועה אין לי neder ushvu'a ein li I don't have
any right to make you take an oath or vow, ולא ליורשי
ve'lo leyorshai or my heirs don't I waive the rights of my
heirs, ולא לבאים ברשותי ve'lo labaim birshuti and I waive the rights
of anybody that's coming well. If they if my heirs go ahead
and make her in charge of the business after I'm dead, then
that's their own arrangement, they can make her take an oath. But
if it's related to things that she was obligated to me, if
it's coming through my power, they can't make her take an I
can say they won't be able to make you take an oath
over any obligation you had to me. Right? Obviously I can't prevent
people from their independently contracted obligations once my power is gone. Right.
Okay. ולא אני ולא יורשי וכל הבאים ברשותי ve'lo ani ve'lo yorshai
ve'chol habaim birshuti and I don't me and my heirs and anybody
that comes through my rights I waive does not have the ability
to make you take an oath, עליך alaich not you, ועל יורשיך
ve'al yorshaich or your heirs, ועל הבאים ברשותך ve'al habaim birshutaich and
those that come through you, in that case אינו יכול להשביע einu
yachol lehashbi'a I cannot make her take an oath, לא הוא ולא
יורשיו ולא הבאים ברשותו lo hu ve'lo yorshav ve'lo habaim birshuto nobody
I sold my business to, again in terms of things in the
past that she was obligated to me about. Okay. לא אותה ולא
יורשיה ולא הבאים ברשותה. lo otah ve'lo yorsheha ve'lo habaim birshuta. הלכה
מקבר בעלה לבית אביה. halcha mikever ba'alah lebeit aviha. Now, her husband
died and she went home to her father's house. או שחזרה לבית
חמיה o shechazra lebeit chamia or she went to her continued living
with her father-in-law, ולא נעשית אפוטרופיא ve'lo na'asit apitropia and she was
not made a there was no new arrangement, all her role of
being in charge of my business was all in the past, Reuven
who died, okay, it was all when he was alive, now that
he's dead she's no longer in charge of the business. So it's
all stuff in the past, all relationship to Reuven, and Reuven waived
the idea of oath. In that case אין היורשים משביעין אותה ein
hayorshim mashbi'in otah then the heirs can't make her take an oath
because Reuven waived all the rights to the oath, okay, and it
was all in the past now. But ואם נעשית אפוטרופיא ve'im na'asit
apitropia now after Reuven's dead the heirs said you're doing such a
good job you should continue running the business, and then for all
the new therefore relationship they can make her take the oath. Okay?
Because that's not affected by Reuven's waiving of the נדר. neder. In
that case היורשים משביעין אותה על העתיד לבוא hayorshim mashbi'in otah al
heatid lavo for all future business, ואין משביעין אותה על מה שעבר.
ve'ein mashbi'in otah al ma she'avar. What? Even by? I don't know
about you anyway, yes, but not on past. So the person can
waive all of his rights but only his rights, not other people's
rights, not other relationships, and like the first משנה you have to
be very explicit or
we'll interpret it in the narrowest way possible. So you have to
be explicit if you want it to apply to all of your
heirs and all those people that come through you and if you
want it to apply to all of her heirs and so on,
otherwise we interpret it very narrowly. Okay, that's it for today. We
can come back tomorrow or as scheduled. What? You've just reached
אפוטרופיא?
apitropia?